{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "As Acting Solicitor General, Neal Katyal released a 2011 statement accusing one of his predecessors, Charles Fahy, of covering up evidence relevant to this case. Justice Frank Murphy’s dissent in this case, along with his concurrence in Steele, marked the first uses of the word “racism” in a Supreme Court opinion. The previous case of Hirabayashi v. United States was found to be controlling in Hugo Black’s majority opinion in this case, which defended Executive Order 9066 as a legitimate use of executive discretion. For ten points, name this 1944 Supreme Court decision that upheld Japanese internment camps.",
      "answer": "Korematsu v. United States"
    },
    {
      "question": "Anaxemanwholegendarilykilled40peopleatthisbattlewashimselfkilledwhenasoldierunderneath the bridge he stood on stabbed him through the planks. One attack during this battle was known as “Orre’s Storm.” This battle, named for a location near the Derwent River, included the deaths of Tostig and the Norwegian king Harald Hardrada. For ten points, name this victory for the forces of Harold Godwinson which preceded the 1066 Battle of Hastings by five days.",
      "answer": "Battle of Stamford Bridge"
    },
    {
      "question": "A king of this dynasty named You disgraced the Marquis of Shen after divorcing his daughter for Bao Si, which led to the sacking of Hao. This dynasty, which was founded in the Wei river valley, won the Battle of Muye against Di Xin [dee shin]. The Eastern version of this dynasty featured the Hundred Schools of Thought during the Spring and Autumn Period, and this dynasty faded when the Warring States were unified into the Qin dynasty. For ten points, name this longest-lasting Chinese dynasty.",
      "answer": [
        "Zhou dynasty",
        "Western Zhao until “Wei” is read, then",
        "Western and/or Eastern Zhao"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "A student at this school was expelled when he said a tutor named Whittlesey “had no more grace than a chair.” While under the leadership of Thomas Clapp, this university faced a conflict between the “Old Lights” and “New Lights.” This university is named after a leader in the British East India Company, but it was known as the Collegiate School while it was located in Saybrook. The Skull and Bones secret society was formed at, for ten points, what Ivy League university that, in 1716, moved to New Haven, Connecticut?",
      "answer": "Yale University"
    },
    {
      "question": "The publication of this work was preceded by a 9-page manuscript titled De motu corporum in gyrum, which was sent to Edmund Halley. The author of this work added a section containing the line “I contrive no hypotheses” to the end of this work’s second edition, referred to as the General Scholium. This work contains a proof of Kepler’s empirically derived laws of planetary motion. For ten points, name this book that introduced the three laws of motion and the law of universal gravitation, written by Sir Isaac Newton.",
      "answer": "Philosophiae Naturalis Principia Mathematica"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man instructed his warriors to sing an enemy victory chant to lure out his opponent’s defenses in the final defeat of his rival, Zwide [zwee-day]. This leader instructed his troops to envelop enemies while attacking in a “buffalo horns” formation and introduced the tactic of offensive shield hooking while using a shorter, stabbing spear called the iklwa. Dingane [din-gah-nay] helped assassinate this chieftain in 1828. For ten points, name this early leader of the Zulu kingdom.",
      "answer": "Shaka Zulu or Shaka kaSenzangakhona"
    },
    {
      "question": "This body’s legislation was stored in the treasury building, called the Aerarium. A common stalling tactic in this body was to continue speaking until nightfall. This body was forbidden from meeting more than a mile from the pomerium. The Catiline Conspiracy was exposed in a meeting of this body, whose actions could be vetoed by tribunes. Its members were appointed by the censors, often after holding offices like aedile and quaestor. For ten points, name this legislative body of Rome.",
      "answer": "Roman Senate"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man depicted Louis de Bourbon brought before William de la Marck in The Murder of the Bishop of Liege. An Assyrian king appears disinterested as his concubines are killed in this man’s Death of Sardanapalus, and he illustrated another slaughter in his Massacre at Chios. This man’s most famous work is set during the July Revolution and depicts Marianne at the front of a ragtag army holding a musket and tricolor. For ten points, name this French painter of Liberty Leading the People.",
      "answer": "Eugene Delacroix"
    },
    {
      "question": "The location of this project was hotly contested by a board chaired for a time by Gouverneur Morris. A series of letters advocating this project were written under the pseudonym “Hercules” by inmate Jesse Hawley. This project required the dangerous and costly draining of Montezuma Marsh. It was derisively nicknamed “Clinton’s Ditch” after then governor of New York DeWitt Clinton. For ten points, identify this waterway that, after 1821, connected Albany to a namesake great lake bordering Buffalo.",
      "answer": "Erie Canal"
    },
    {
      "question": "Description acceptable. A key piece of evidence in this lawsuit was the “Porter Presentation,” which supposedly made Pete Rozelle “physically ill.” Though the plaintiff in this case was awarded victory, the jury only awarded damages of one dollar, which was tripled because the case involved antitrust law. In the aftermath of this case, Donald Trump’s New Jersey Generals and other teams suspended operations. For ten points, name this lawsuit filed by the USFL against its primary competitor, which was found to have created an anti-competitive business environment.",
      "answer": [
        "NFL monopoly case",
        "United States Football League v. National Football League,",
        "USFL v. NFL,",
        "descriptions of “the USFL’s lawsuit,” before USFL is named",
        "antitrust for monopoly before antitrust is mentioned"
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A Senator from Maine named William Frye was one negotiator of this treaty, whose fifth article limited the commissions of both sides to five people. One year before this treaty was signed, one side had signed the Pact of Biak-no-Bato with a revolutionary group. The Platt Amendment concerned a territory ceded by this treaty, which gave Puerto Rico and Guam to the United States. One side relinquished Cuba in, for ten points, what 1898 treaty ending the Spanish-American War?",
        "answer": [
          "Treaty of Paris of 1898 BONUS:TheaforementionedPactofBaik-na-BatowassignedbySpanishdiplomatsandthisrevolutionary Philippine leader, who became the first President of the Philippines two years later. ANSWER: Emilio Aguinaldo 2 This man and his armor-bearer defeated an entire garrison at Michmash",
          "immediately afterwards, this man broke his father’s decree of an army-wide fast by eating honey from the ground. This man shot three arrows as a signal for his brother-in-law, whom he loved “as himself,” to flee. This man died with his brothers and father at the Battle of Mount Gilboa while fighting the Philistines. Modern Christian debates regarding homosexuality often consider, for ten points, what oldest son of King Saul of Israel who held a covenant of friendship with David? ANSWER: Jonathan",
          "Yehonatan",
          "Yonatan"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This author cited the relationship between David and Jonathan in support of his homosexuality during his 1895 trial.",
        "answer": "Oscar Wilde"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This politician’s brother, Erik Prince, founded the private military firm Academi, originally named Blackwater. In a Congressional hearing, this politician was mocked for praising guns for defense in case of bear attacks. Susan Collins and Lisa Murkowski crossed party lines to vote against this figure’s confirmation, requiring the tie to be broken by Mike Pence. For ten points, name this proponent of charter schools and current US Secretary of Education.",
        "answer": "Betsy DeVos"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "DeVos was slammed in February for claiming that these institutions were “real pioneers of school choice.” A visit by leaders of these institutions to the Oval Office was marked by images of Kellyanne Conway using her phone while kneeling on a sofa.",
        "answer": [
          "historically black colleges and/or universities",
          "HBCs, HBUs,",
          "HBCUs"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "One holder of this position expanded his capital city to include Janiculum Hill, while another holder of this position created the Tribal Assembly for the lower classes. Holders of this position repeatedly fought against Veii [way-ee] and destroyed the city of Alba Longa. The last holder of this position was overthrown by Lucius Junius Brutus after the Rape of Lucretia. Julius Caesar was assassinated because the conspirators thought he wanted to revive, for ten points, what position held by the first seven rulers of Rome?",
        "answer": "King of Rome"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The last three kings of Rome were descendants of this civilization, which dominated Italy before the rise of Rome.",
        "answer": "Etruscans"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "An event in this US state was the subject of Heather Ann Thompson’s 2016 book Blood in the Water and was discussed by the mostly sealed Meyer Report. A 19th century facility in this state developed a system of solitary confinement and prison labor called the Auburn system. William Quinn was one of ten corrections officers killed in this state in a 1971 prison riot that ended with this state’s police killing 33 prisoners. For ten points, name this state where Governor Nelson Rockefeller put down the Attica prison riot.",
        "answer": "New York"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In addition to the Auburn and Attica prisons, this other New York prison housed an electric chair nicknamed “Old Sparky” where Julius and Ethel Rosenberg were executed in 1953.",
        "answer": [
          "Sing Sing Correctional Facility",
          "Ossining Correctional Facility"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Although not the unconscious, Cote and Levine studied the “collective” form of this concept. It was broken down into 8 separate challenges by a psychologist who wrote biographies of Mohandas Gandhi and Martin Luther focused on this concept. Stages of this psychological concept, which include autonomy vs. shame and industry vs. inferiority, were included in Erik Erikson’s model of it. For ten points, name this psychological concept of one’s self, which can experience a namesake “crisis.”",
        "answer": "identity"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This Roman politician experienced one of history’s first recorded identity crises upon crying while looking at a statue of Alexander the Great at the age of 31.",
        "answer": "Gaius Julius Caesar"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This ruler ordered the execution of Waldensians at the Massacre of M´erindol. After this ruler’s victory at the Battle of Marignano, this leader signed the Perpetual Peace with Switzerland. This ruler’s blockade of Nice was aided by an Ottoman fleet, to which he had leased the port of Toulon. This man reneged on the Treaty of Madrid, which had ceded Burgundy and Provence to his neighbor, as soon as he was released from captivity. For ten points, name this French king of the Valois dynasty who lost the Battle of Pavia to Charles V.",
        "answer": "Francis I or Fran¸cois I"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Francis partied with his rival Henry VIII at this site in 1520, where he sought an alliance. At this location, Francis defeated Henry in a wrestling match, wounding his ego.",
        "answer": "Field of the Cloth of Gold"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In this country, Roger East was executed while investigating the deaths of the Balibo Five. The Laksaur militia committed the Suai Church Massacre after a pro-independence referendum in this country, which was advocated for by Nobel Laureate Jos´e Ramos-Horta. This country’s FRETILIN party was represented by Horta at the UN during its occupation by a country that committed the Dili massacre. For ten points, name this country that was occupied by Indonesia from 1975 until its 2002 independence.",
        "answer": "East Timor"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Jose Ramos-Horta shared the 1996 Nobel Peace Prize for advocating independence with Carlos Belo, who represented this organization. The 1979 Nobel Peace Prize winner founded a subgroup of this organization known as “M.C.” in Calcutta.",
        "answer": "Roman Catholic Church"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "Civil Rights Movement",
      "prompt": "What...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Man gave the “I Have a Dream” speech and was assassinated by James Earl Ray?",
          "answer": "Dr. Martin Luther King Jr. or MLK"
        },
        {
          "question": "Woman refused to give up her seat on a bus, prompting the Montgomery Bus Boycott?",
          "answer": "Rosa Parks"
        },
        {
          "question": "Governor of Alabama promised “segregation now, segregation tomorrow, segregation forever”?",
          "answer": "George Wallace"
        },
        {
          "question": "Man was the first black student admitted to the University of Mississippi?",
          "answer": "James Meredith"
        },
        {
          "question": "City was the starting point of a 1965 march to Montgomery during which protesters were beaten on the Edmund Pettus Bridge?",
          "answer": "Selma, Alabama"
        },
        {
          "question": "Former SNCC chair wrote the 2013 memoir March?",
          "answer": "John Lewis"
        },
        {
          "question": "Supreme Court case established that the Commerce Clause allowed the Civil Rights Act to prohibit segregation in public accommodations?",
          "answer": "Heart of Atlanta Motel, Inc. v United States"
        },
        {
          "question": "Political party formed in 1964 to replace Mississippi’s all-white delegation to the 1964 DNC?",
          "answer": "Mississippi Freedom Democratic Party do not"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Marxism",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "1848 work by Marx and Engels that put forward their theories of class struggle.",
          "answer": "The Communist Manifesto"
        },
        {
          "question": "Economic system that a society is required to pass through before a socialist revolution; it is dominated by the bourgoisie and business interests.",
          "answer": [
            "capitalism",
            "word forms"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Term Marx used to describe the working classes.",
          "answer": [
            "proletariats",
            "proles"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Religious minority often blamed for communism, since they were prominently represented in Bolshevik leadership. Marx and Trotsky belonged to this group.",
          "answer": "Jewish people"
        },
        {
          "question": "Socialist government in Paris in 1871 that formed in response to the French defeat in the Franco- Prussian War.",
          "answer": "Paris Commune"
        },
        {
          "question": "1919 Marxist uprising that helped bring down the German monarchy.",
          "answer": "Spartacist Uprising or Revolt, etc."
        },
        {
          "question": "TheoryassociatedwithTrotskythatadvocatesfortheworkingclassestobeinalong,uncompromising state to overthrow the ruling classes.",
          "answer": "permanent revolution"
        },
        {
          "question": "Work by Marx arguing against a German political platform. The quote “from each according to his ability, to each according to his needs” comes from this work.",
          "answer": "Critique of the Gotha Program"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Mughal Empire",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "European power that cooperated with the Mughals and governed its overseas ports from Lisbon.",
          "answer": "Portugal"
        },
        {
          "question": "Mausoleum built by Mughal ruler Shah Jahan for his wife Mumtaz at Agra.",
          "answer": "Taj Mahal"
        },
        {
          "question": "Company that eventually conquered India from the Mughals. It won the Battle of Plassey against the Nawab of Bengal.",
          "answer": "British East India Company"
        },
        {
          "question": "Third ruler of the Empire, who repealed the jizya tax and created his own religion.",
          "answer": "Akbar the Great"
        },
        {
          "question": "Persian rival of the Mughals, located to the west. It was founded by Ismail I, a Shi’ite.",
          "answer": "Safavid Empire"
        },
        {
          "question": "Residence of the Mughal Emperors in Old Delhi. It was plundered during the 1739 sack of Delhi.",
          "answer": "Red Fort"
        },
        {
          "question": "Confederacy that displaced the Mughals from southern India. It was founded by Shivaji.",
          "answer": "Maratha Confederacy"
        },
        {
          "question": "Last great Mughal Emperor, a son of Shah Jahan who ruled over the empire at its greatest extent.",
          "answer": "Aurangzeb or Alamgir I"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) During this battle, Simon Bolivar Buckner was killed by an explosion that sent coral into his body. Underage children were drafted into the Iron and Blood Imperial Corps in preparation for this battle. The battleship (20 pts)",
        "Yamato was sunk in this battle, which was nicknamed the “typhoon of steel” due to the heavy incidence of kamikaze attacks. During this battle, one side launched Operation Iceberg in an attempt to gain a (10 pts)",
        "base of operations for the invasion of the Japanese mainland. For ten points, name this 1945 battle in the Ryukyu Islands in the conclusion of the Allied island hopping campaign."
      ],
      "answer": "Battle of Okinawa"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This island is home to a Methodist camp known for its gingerbread cottages, Wesleyan Grove. This island, which comprises the bulk of Dukes County, was home to a village sign language that died out in the 1950s. John F. Kennedy Jr. (20 pts)",
        "died in a plane crash off this island’s coast, and depending on tides, this island is sometimes connected to a smaller island where (10 pts)",
        "Mary Jo Kopechne died in the Chappaquiddick Incident. For ten points, name this resort island off the south coast of mainland Massachusetts and west of Nantucket."
      ],
      "answer": "Martha’s Vineyard"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Hymn 10.13 of a work written in this language is interpreted as expressing either monotheism, atheism, or polytheism. Arthur Schopenhauer’s translations of several works in this language led him to call them the “production of the highest human wisdom.” (20 pts)",
        "Robert Oppenheimer supposedly learned this language just to read one of its most famous works, which he quoted after the Trinity nuclear test. The (10 pts)",
        "Upanishads, Bhagavad Gita, and Mahabharata were all written in, for ten points, what ancient Indian language used in Hindu, Buddhist, and Jain traditions?"
      ],
      "answer": "Sanskrit"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) One performer of this instrument wrote a song in protest of a segregationist Governor of Arkansas that was originally recorded as an instrumental, “Fables of Faubus.” That performer of this instrument also wrote the prehistoric-themed jazz tone poem (20 pts)",
        "Pithecanthropus Erectus. Charlie Haden played this instrument, as did the composer of The Black Saint and the Sinner Lady, Charles (10 pts)",
        "Mingus. This instrument can play a “walking” line and is often played with a “slap” pizzicato in jazz. For ten points, name this largest and lowest-pitched string instrument."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "double bass or upright bass",
        "acoustic bass"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) These people gained independence following the War of the Thuringian Succession, though they would later form unions with cities like Kassel and Marburg. A king of these people, Philip, lost the Battle of Mulhberg while leading the (20 pts)",
        "Schmalkaldic League against Charles V. In another war, a force of these people were attacked by troops using the call-sign “victory or death;” in that attack, (10 pts)",
        "Johann Rall led a group of these people that were ambushed after an opposing general crossed an icy river on Christmas night. For ten points, name these German mercenaries who fought for England in the Revolutionary War and were ambushed when Washington crossed the Delaware."
      ],
      "answer": "Hessians"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In an epic poem set in this country, a group of exiles send a message to an old leader by writing their names on a thousand pieces of wood and casting them into the sea. While sick, the body of an evil poetic character from this country is so feverish that it turns (20 pts)",
        "water to fire. A poem from this country is about a hut that “May change with a new owner / Into a doll’s house” and opens the collection (10 pts)",
        "Narrow Road to the Deep North. The Taira and Minamoto clans clash in The Tale of the Heike, an epic poem from this country. For ten points, name this home country of Matsuo Basho, a poet who wrote many haiku."
      ],
      "answer": "Japan"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A speech by this man begins with an analogy in which a mariner is advised to take heed of his latitude after being tossed about in a storm. This man lost popularity in his home region after a lengthy speech that ends by reciting the inscription on the (20 pts)",
        "Shield of Achilles. This man declared “Liberty and Union, now and for ever, one and inseparable” as part of a debate in which he opposed (10 pts)",
        "nullification. For ten points, name this Massachusetts senatorwhodeliveredtheSeventhofMarchspeechandtheSecondReplytoHayneandservedasSecretary of State."
      ],
      "answer": "Daniel Webster"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) On the way to this event, the victim was given a book of psalms by Henry Edgeworth. A publication called the Daily Thermometer claimed that the victim of this event exclaimed “I am lost!” Antoine-Joseph Santerre hastened this event by calling a (20 pts)",
        "drumroll, drowning out its victim’s speech. Charles-Henri Sanson carried out this event, one and a half years after its victim was recognized by Jean-Bapiste Drouet during the (10 pts)",
        "flight to Varennes and nine months before its victim’s wife suffered the same fate. The guillotine was employed in, for ten points, what 1793 killing of a French monarch?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "execution of Louis XVI",
        "equivalents for execution, including beheading, killing, etc."
      ]
    }
  ]
}